Guide to the William Bowyer Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Bowyer papers
1674-1874
OSB MSS 105
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.33
(2 boxes)
Correspondence and other papers relating to William Bowyer's (1699-1777) work as a printer in London. The bulk of the correspondence consists of incoming letters to Bowyer from the scholars Edward Clarke, William Clarke, and Jeremiah Markland, concerning printing, scholarly subjects, languanges including Greek and Hebrew, and family matters. Other correspondents include James Stanier Clarke, Catherine Markland, William Strode, Moses Williams, and William Wotten. Also includes two items written by Bowyer and a few letters addressed to Bowyer's apprentice and partner John Nichols. Letters prior to 1737 may have been addressed to the elder William Bowyer. Two letters in latin, signed "Ambrosius Bonvicus," were probably written by Ambrose Bonwicke as a student at St. John's College, Oxford. Other Papers include a manuscript address for a Mr. Stawell to give to the Duchess of York, an engraving of William Bowyer, an 1874 collection inventory by James Crossley, and proof sheets of an unidentified history of Bowyer's printing business.
Bowyer, William, 1699-1777
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Manuscripts and Archives, October 1980.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
WILLIAM BOWYER, 1699-1777
William Bowyer (1699-1777) was the son of printer William Bowyer (1663-1737). He was placed by his father as a sizar at St. John's College, Cambridge, in 1716. Without finishing his degree, Bowyer began working for his father in 1722. Bowyer often printed scholarly and literary works. In 1729 he was appointed to print votes of the House of Commons, and in 1761 was appointed printer for the Royal Society. He also wrote and published some of his own works. A notable apprentice of Bowyers's was John Nichols, whom Bowyer later made a full partner.
Scope and Contents
The William Bowyer Papers consist of correspondence and other papers related to William Bowyer (1699-1777), a prominent London printer during the eighteenth century. The papers, which span the years 1674-1874, are housed in 2 boxes (including 1 oversize box), and have been organized into two series: Correspondence, and Other Papers.
Series I, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent in folders 1-32, and 39-42 (oversize). The correspondence consists of incoming letters to William Bowyer, as well as two items written by Bowyer, and a few letters addressed to his partner John Nichols. Letters written prior to 1737 may have been addressed to the elder William Bowyer (1763-1737).
The bulk of the correspondence is from William Clarke, his son Edward Clarke, and Jeremiah Markland. All three were scholars and their letters concern printing, various scholarly subjects, languages, including Greek and Hebrew, and family matters. Edward Clarke's correspondence includes three letters to John Nichols after Bowyers's death in 1777.
Additional correspondents include Edward Clarke's son James Stanier Clarke; Jeremiah Markland's sister Catherine Markland; William Strode, a friend and student of Jeremiah Markland; Welsh scholar Moses Williams; and scholar William Wotten, William Clarke's father-in-law. The correspondence also includes two letters written in Latin to unidentified recipients. Signed "Ambrosius Bonvicus," the letters were probably written by Ambrose Bonwicke (1652-1722) as a student at St. John's College, Oxford.
Series II, Other Papers, is arranged chronologically in folders 33-38. Other papers consist of a manuscript address for a Mr. Stawell to give to the Duchess of York, an engraving of William Bowyer, an 1874 collection inventory by James Crossley, proof sheets of an unidentified history of Bowyer's printing business, a manuscript list of letters "written before Mr. B's father died," and the binding from which these papers were disbound.
Philology; Printers -- England -- London; Printing -- Great Britain -- 17th-18th centuries; Printers -- Great Britain; Bonwicke, Ambrose, 1652-1722; Bowyer, William, 1663-1737; Bowyer, William, 1699-1777; Clarke, Edward, 1730-1786; Clarke, James Stanier, 1765?-1834; Clarke, William, 1696-1771; Markland, Catherine; Markland, Jeremiah, 1693-1776; Nichols, John, 1745-1826; Strode, William, 1600 or 1601-1645; Williams, Moses, 1685-1742; Wotton, William, 1666-1727
- Correspondence, 1674-1782; Series I; 36
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically.
  - Bonwicke, Ambrose, 1674 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    In Latin
  - Bowyer, William, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clarke, Edward, 1755-82 (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
  - Clarke, James Stanier, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clarke, William, 1726-58 (Box 1, Folder 8-13)
  - Clarke, William, 1762-71, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14-20)
  - Markland, Catherine, 1776-79
  - Markland, Jeremiah, 1743-76 (Box 1, Folder 21-29)
  - Strode, William, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Williams, Moses, 1734-36 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Wotten, William, 1725 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Other Papers, 1683-1874; Series II; 6
  Series II, Other Papers, is arranged chronologically.
  - Manuscript address, "For Mr. Stawell to be spoke to Her R. H. the Dutchess of Y. in the inner Library, May 1683", 1683 May (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Includes Latin translation
  - Engraving of William Bowyer, printed by J. Nichols & Son, 1812 Jan 1 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Collection inventory by James Crossley, 1874 Dec 8 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Includes note stating that Crossley purchased the collection "at John Gough Nichols's Sale"
  - Proof sheets of an unidentified history of Bowyer's printing business, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Manuscript list of "most of the letters written before Mr. B's father died", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Previous binding (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Binding labelled "Markland and Clarke's Letters to Bowyer"
- Oversize, 1753-79
  - Clarke, Edward correspondence (in Series I), 1753-79 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 39)
  - Clarke, William correspondence (in Series I), 1726-69 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 40)
  - Markland, Catherine correspondence (in Series I), 1776-1779 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 41)
  - Markland, Jeremiah correspondence (in Series I), 1767 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 42)